The following content is
provided under a Creative Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue
to offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional
materials from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT
OpenCourseWare at ocw .mit .edu.
So this is a big day mathematically
speaking, because we come to this key idea,
which is a little bit like eigenvalues,
well, a lot like eigenvalues, but different
because the matrix A
now
is usually rectangular.
So for a rectangular matrix, the whole idea
of eigenvalues
is shot, because if I multiply A
times a vector x in n
dimensions, out will come something in m dimensions, and it's not going
to equal lambda x. So Ax equal lambda x is not even possible if A is
rectangular.
And even if A is square,
what are the problems? Just thinking for a
minute about eigenvalues.
The case I wrote up here
is the
great case where I have a symmetric matrix,
and then it's got
a full set of eigenvalues and eigenvectors,
and they're
orthogonal, all good.
But for a general square matrix,
either the eigenvectors are complex, eigenvalues
are complex, or the eigenvectors are not orthogonal.
So we can't stay with eigenvalues forever. That's
what I'm saying. And this is the right thing to do.
Now, so what are these pieces?
So these are the left,
and these are the
right singular vectors.
So this is the
new word is singular.
And
in between go not the eigenvalues, but the
singular values.
So we've got the whole
point now. You've got to pick up on this.
There are two sets
of singular vectors, not one.
For eigenvectors, we just
had one set,
the q's.
Now we have, for
a rectangular matrix,
we've got one set of left eigenvectors in m
dimensions,
and we've got another
set of right eigenvectors in n dimensions.
And numbers in between are not eigenvalues,
but singular values.
So these guys are,
let
me write what that looks
like. This is, again, a diagonal matrix,
sigma 2 to sigma r,
let's say.
So it's, again, a diagonal
matrix in the middle.
But
the
numbers on that diagonal are all positive,
or 0.
And they're called singular values. So it's
just a different world.
OK,
so really the first step I have to do, the
math step, is to show that any matrix
can
be factored into
u times sigma times v transpose.
So that's the parallel to the spectral theorem that
any symmetric matrix could be factored that way.
So you're good for that part.
We just have to do it
to see what
are u and sigma and v.
What are those vectors
and those singular values? OK, let's go.
So the key is
that A transpose A
is a great matrix. So that's the key to the
math,
is A transpose A.
So what are the properties of
A transpose A? This A is rectangular again.
So maybe
m by n.
A transpose
is, so this was m by n.
This was n by m.
So we get a
result that's n by n.
And what else can
you tell me about A transpose A?
Symmetric. It's symmetric. That's
a big deal.
And it's square.
And well, oh, yeah, you can tell me more
now. Because we talked about something,
a topic that's
a little more than symmetric last
time.
The matrix A transpose A will be
positive definite. Its
eigenvalues are greater or equal 0.
And
that will mean that we
can take their square roots.
And that's what we will do.
So A transpose A
will have a factorization. It's symmetric.
It'll have like a
q lambda q transpose.
But I'm going to call it v lambda.
No, yeah, lambda. I'll still call it lambda
v transpose.
So these v's, what do we know about the eigenvectors?
So these v's are eigenvectors of this guy.
Square, symmetric, positive
definite matrix. So we're in good shape.
And what do we know about the eigenvalues
of A transpose A? They are all positive.
So the eigenvalues
are, well, are equal 0.
And these guys are orthogonal.
And these
guys are greater or equal there.
And OK.
So that's good.
That's one of our, we'll depend a lot on that. But also,
you've got to recognize that A A transpose is a different guy.
A A transpose.
So what's the
shape of A A transpose?
How big is that?
Now I've got,
what do I have? M by
N times N by M. So this will be what size?
M by M. Different shape.
But with the same eigenvalues.
The same eigenvalues. So
it's going to have some other eigenvectors,
u. Of course, I'm going to call them u, because
I'm going to go in over there. They'll be the same.
Well, the same, yeah,
I shouldn't,
I have to say,
when I say the same,
I can't quite literally mean the very same, because this
has got N eigenvalues, and this has got M eigenvalues.
But the missing guys, the ones that are in one of
them and not in the other, depending on the sizes,
are 0s.
So really, the
heart of the thing, the
non -zero eigenvalues are the same.
OK.
Now, well, actually,
I've pretty much revealed
what the SVD is going to use.
It's going to use the u's
from here and the v's from here. But that's
the story. You've got to see that story.
So fresh start on the singular value
decomposition. What are we looking for?
Well, as a factorization,
so we're looking for,
we want A,
we want vectors v,
so that when I multiply by v,
so if it was an
eigenvector, it would be Av equal lambda v.
But now for A, it's rectangular. It hasn't
got eigenvectors.
So Av is sigma,
the new singular value, times u.
So I'm going to take the first guy and the
second guy and the rth guy. I'll stop at r,
the rank.
Oh, yeah.
Is that what I want?
Let me just see.
Av is sigma
u. Yeah, that's good. OK.
So this is
what takes the place of Ax equal lambda x.
A times one set
of singular vectors gives me a number times the other
set of singular vectors. And why did I stop at r,
the rank?
Because after that, the sigmas are 0.
So after that, I could have some more guys.
But they'll
be in the null space,
on down
to vn.
So these are the important ones.
That's what I'm looking for.
Let me say it now in words.
I'm looking for a bunch
of orthogonal vectors, v,
so that when
I multiply them by A,
I get a bunch of
orthogonal vectors u.
That is not
so clearly possible. But it is possible. It
does happen.
I'm looking for one set of orthogonal
vectors v in the input space, you could say,
so that the
Av's in the output space
are also orthogonal.
In our picture of the big picture of linear
algebra,
we have
v's
in this space
and then stuff in the
null space.
Over here in the column space and
some stuff in the null space over there.
And the idea is that I have orthogonal v's
here.
And when I multiply by
A, so multiply
by A,
then I get orthogonal
u's over here.
Orthogonal to orthogonal.
That's
what makes
the v's and the u's special.
Right.
OK, that's the property. And then when we write
down, well, let me write down what that would mean.
So
I've just drawn a picture to go with this,
those equations.
That picture just goes
with these equations.
And let me just write
down what it means.
It means
in matrix,
so
I've
written it, oh, yeah. I've written it here
in vectors one at a time.
But of course, you know I'm going to put
those vectors into the columns of a matrix.
So A times
v1 up to, let's say, vr
will equal,
oh, yeah, it
equals sigma times u's.
So this is what I'm after,
is u1 up to
ur multiplied by sigma 1 along to sigma r.
What I'm doing now is
just to say I'm converting these individual
singular vectors,
each v going into a u,
to putting them all together into a matrix. And of
course, what I've written here is Av equals u sigma.
Av equals u sigma.
That's what that amounts to.
Well,
then
I'm going to put a v transpose on this side. And
I'm going to get to A equals u sigma v transpose,
multiplying both sides
there by v transpose.
Kind of writing the same thing in different
forms, matrix form, vector at a time form.
And now we
have to find them. Now I've
used up boards saying what we're after, but
now we've got to get there.
So what are the v's
and what are the u's?
Well,
the cool
idea is to think of A transpose A.
So you're
with me what we're for.
And now think about A
transpose A.
So if this is what I'm
hoping for,
what will
A transpose A turn out to be?
So big moment
that's going to reveal
what the v's are.
So if I form A transpose A,
so A
transpose, I've got to transpose this guy.
So A transpose is
v sigma transpose u transpose, right?
And then comes A, which is this,
u sigma v transpose.
So why did I do that?
Why is it that A transpose A is the cool
thing to look at to make the problem simpler?
Well, what
becomes simpler in that line just written?
u transpose u is
the identity,
because I'm looking for
orthogonal, in fact, orthonormal u's.
So that's the identity. So this
is v
sigma transpose sigma
v transpose.
And I'll put parentheses around that,
because that's a diagonal matrix.
What does that tell me?
What does that tell all of us?
A transpose A has this form. Now, we've seen that form before. We know
that this is a symmetric matrix, symmetric and even positive definite.
So what are the v's?
The v's are
the eigenvectors of A
transpose A.
This is the q lambda q
transpose for that symmetric matrix.
So we know the v's are
the eigenvectors
of A transpose A.
And I guess we're also going to get the singular
value. So the sigma transpose sigma, which will be
the sigma squareds,
are the eigenvalues
of A transpose A.
Good.
Sort of by looking for the correct thing, u sigma v transpose, and then
just using the u transpose u equal identity, we got it back to something we
perfectly recognize.
A transpose A has that form. So now we know
what the v's are. And if I do it the other way,
which what's the other way?
Instead of A transpose A,
the other way is to look at A A transpose.
And if I write all that down,
A is the u sigma v transpose. And the A
transpose is the v sigma transpose u transpose.
And this stuff goes away and leaves me with
u
sigma sigma transpose u
transpose. So I know what the u's are too.
They're the eigenvectors
of A A transpose.
Isn't
that a beautiful symmetry?
And A A transpose are two different guys now. So they
have each has its own eigenvectors. And we use both.
It's just right.
And I
just have to take the final step. And we've
established the SVD.
So the final step is to
remember what I'm going for here.
A times a v is supposed to be sigma times a
u.
See, what I have to
deal with now is I haven't quite finished.
It's just perfect as far as
it goes, but it hasn't gone to the end yet.
Because
we could have double eigenvalues and triple
eigenvalues and all those horrible possibilities.
And if I have triple eigenvalues or double
eigenvalues,
then what's the deal with eigenvectors if I
have double eigenvalues? Suppose a matrix has a,
say,
a symmetric matrix
has a double eigenvalue.
Let me just take an example.
So symmetric matrix like,
say, 1, 1, 5. Make it.
Why not?
What's the
deal with eigenvectors
for
that matrix 1, 1, 5?
So 5 has
got an eigenvector. You can see what it is.
0, 0, 1.
What about the eigenvectors that
go
with lambda
equal 1 for that matrix?
What would be eigenvectors for lambda equal
1?
Unfortunately, there's
a whole plane of them.
Any vector
of the form x, y, 0. Any vector in the x, y
plane would produce x, y, 0.
And vectors. And
I've got to pick two that
are orthogonal, which I can do. And
then they have to be in the SVD.
Those two orthogonal guys have to go to two
orthogonal guys.
In other words,
there's a little bit
of detail here.
A little getting into this
exactly what is.
Well,
actually,
let me. Let me
tell you the steps.
OK.
So I use this to conclude that the v's, the
singular vectors, should be eigenvalues.
I concluded those guys from this step. Now,
I'm not going to use this step so much.
Of course, it's in the back of my mind. But
I'm not
using it.
I'm going to
get the u's from here.
So u1 is a
v1 over sigma 1.
v, ur is a vr over sigma r.
You see what I'm doing here?
I'm picking
in a possible
plane of things the one I want,
the u's I want.
I've chosen the sigmas.
They are
fixed for A transpose A.
The eigenvectors are v's.
The eigenvalues are sigma
squared.
OK.
And now, then,
this is the u I want.
Are you with me?
So I had
to give a, I want to get these u's correct.
And if I have a whole plane of possibilities,
I've got to pick the right one.
OK. And now, finally,
I have to show that it's the right one.
So what is left to show?
I should show that these
u's are eigenvectors of A A transpose.
And I should show
that they're orthogonal.
Right? That's the key, right? I would like
to show that these are orthogonal.
And that's what
goes in this picture.
The v's, I've got orthogonal guys, because
they're the eigenvectors of a symmetric matrix.
Pick them orthogonal. But now, I'm multiplying by A. So I'm
getting the u, which is A v over sigma for the basis vectors.
And I
have to show they're orthogonal.
So this is
like the final moment.
Does everything come together
right?
If I've picked the v's
as the eigenvectors of
A transpose A,
and then I take these
for the u's,
are they orthogonal?
So I would like to think that we can check
that fact and
that it will come out.
Could you just help me
through this one?
I'll never
ask for anything again.
Just get the SVD for me.
OK.
So I would like to show
that
u1, that's so let me put up what I'm doing.
I'm trying to show that u1 transpose u2 is
0.
They're orthogonal.
OK, so u1 is A v1
over sigma 1.
That's transpose. That's u1.
And u2 is A v2 over sigma 2.
And I want to get 0.
The whole conversation is
ending right here.
Why is that thing 0?
The v's are orthogonal.
We know the v's are orthogonal.
They're orthogonal eigenvectors of A transpose A. Let
me repeat that. The v's are orthogonal eigenvectors
of A transpose A,
which I know we can find them. Then I chose the
u's to be this. And I want to get the answer 0.
Are you ready to do it?
We want to compute that
and get 0. So what do I get?
We just have to do it.
So I can see that the denominator is that.
So is it v1 transpose
A transpose, right,
times A v2?
And I'm hoping to get 0.
Do I get 0 here?
You hope so.
v1 is orthogonal to v2. But I've got
A transpose A stuck in the middle there.
So what happens here?
How do I look at that?
I've got v2 squared
times v2,
yep, divided by sigma 1 sigma 2.
So the A's are out of there now.
And do I?
So I've just got these numbers,
sigma 2 squared. So that would
be sigma 2 over sigma 1. I've accounted for
these numbers here,
times v1 transpose v2.
And now
what's up?
They're orthonormal.
We've got it.
That's 0.
That is 0 there.
Yeah. So not
only are the v's orthogonal to each other,
but because they're eigenvectors of A transpose A, when I do this,
I discover that the Av's are orthogonal to each other over in the
column space.
So orthogonal
v's in the row space,
orthogonal Av's over in the column space.
That was discovered long after eigenvectors.
And it's an interesting history.
And it just comes out right.
And then it was discovered, but
not much used for, oh, 100 years probably.
And then
people saw that it was exactly the right thing. And data
matrices became important, which are large rectangular matrices.
And we have not, oh, I better say a word,
just a word here about actually computing
the v's and
the sigmas and the u's.
So how would
you actually find them?
Well, what most want to
say is you would not go
this A transpose A route.
Why is it like a big mistake if you have a
matrix A, say, 5 ,000 by 10 ,000?
Why is it a mistake to actually use A transpose A
in the computation? We used it heavily in the proof.
And we could find another proof that wouldn't use
it so much. But why would I not multiply these
two together?
It's very big, very expensive.
It adds in a
whole lot of round off.
You have a matrix that's now,
its vulnerability to round
off errors is squared.
That's called its condition number
gets squared. And you just don't go there.
So the
actual computational methods are quite
different. And we'll talk about those.
But the A transpose A,
because it's symmetric positive definite,
made the proof so nice. That's what you've
seen the nicest proof, I'd say, of the.
And now I
should think about the geometry.
So
what does A equal A equal u sigma? Maybe I
take another board, but it will
fill it.
But it's a good u sigma
v transpose.
So it's got three factors there.
And I would like, and
each factor is kind of a special matrix.
u and v are orthogonal matrix.
Those as rotations.
Sigma is a diagonal
matrix. I think of it as stretching.
So now I'm just going
to draw the picture.
So here's unit vectors.
And the first thing, so
if I multiply
by x, this is the first thing that happens.
So that rotates.
Here's x's.
And v transpose x's,
that's still a circle.
Length didn't change for those when
I multiply by an orthogonal matrix.
But
the vectors turn.
It's a rotation.
Could be a reflection, but let's keep it as
a rotation.
Now what does sigma do?
So I
have this unit circle. I'm in 2D.
So I'm drawing a picture of the,
vectors,
these are the unit vectors in 2D,
x, y.
They got turned by
the orthogonal matrix.
What does sigma do to
that picture?
It stretches. It stretches. Because sigma multiplies by sigma 1 in the
first component, sigma 2 in the second. So it stretches these guys.
And let's suppose this is number 1 and this
is number 2.
This is number 1
and this is number 2.
Sigma 1, our convention is sigma 1, we always take sigma 1 greater or
equal sigma 2 greater or equal whatever greater or equal sigma rank.
And they're all positive.
And the rest are 0.
So sigma 1 will be bigger than sigma 2. So I'm expecting this ellipse,
it'll change. A circle goes to an ellipse when you stretch the,
I didn't get it quite
perfect, but not bad.
So this would be sigma
2 v2, sigma 1 v1.
And this would be sigma 2 v2.
And we now have an ellipse.
So we started
with x's in a circle.
We rotated.
We stretched.
And now the final step
is take these guys and multiply them by u.
So this was
the sigma
v transpose x.
And now I'm ready
for the u part, which
comes last because it's
at the left.
And what
happens? What's the picture now?
What does u do to the ellipse?
It rotates it.
It's another orthogonal matrix.
It rotates it somewhere,
maybe there.
And now
we see the u's, u2 and u1.
Maybe they're there. Maybe I,
well, let me think about that.
Basically, that's not,
that's right.
So this SVD is telling
us something quite remarkable,
that every
linear transformation, every matrix
multiplication factors into a rotation
times a stretch times
a different rotation,
possibly different.
Actually, when would
the u be the same as the v? Here's a good question. When is u the same as
v? When are the two singular vectors just the same? a is square. GILBERT
STRANGER.
Because a would have to be square.
And we want this to be the same as q lambda
q transpose,
if they're the same.
So the u's would be the same as the
v's when the matrix is symmetric.
And actually, we need
it to be positive definite. Why is that?
Because the convention is these
guys are greater or equal to 0. These guys,
if it's going to be the same,
then
so for a
positive definite symmetric matrix,
the s that we started
with is the same as the a on the next line.
Yeah. The q is
the u. The q transpose is the v transpose.
The lambda is the sigma.
The sewn Those are these good matrices. And they're the ones that you can't
improve, basically. They are so good you can't make a positive definite
symmetric matrix better
than it is. Well, maybe
diagonalize it or something.
Now,
I think I would like one question
here.
It helps me anyway to
keep this figure straight.
the
parameters
in
this factorization.
So I'm 2 by 2.
I'm 2 by 2.
So A
has
four numbers, A, B, C, D.
Then I guess I feel that
four numbers should appear
on the right -hand side.
Somehow the u and the
sigma and the v transpose
should use up a total of four numbers. So we have a nice counting match
between the left side that's got four numbers, A, B, C, D, and the right side
that's
got four numbers buried in there somewhere.
So can we dig them out?
How many numbers in sigma?
That's pretty clear.
Two.
Sigma 1 and sigma 2.
The two eigenvalues.
How many
numbers in this rotation?
So if
I had a different color chalk, I would put
2 for the number of
things accounted for by sigma. How many
parameters does a 2 by 2 rotation require?
1.
And what's a
good word for that 1?
That 1 parameter.
It's like I have a cos theta, sine theta, minus
sine theta, cos theta. There's a number theta.
It's the angle it rotates.
So
that's one guy to tell the rotation angle,
two guys to
tell the stretchings, and
one more to
tell the rotation from u,
adding up to 4.
So those match up with the four numbers, A, B, C,
D, that we start with. Of course, it's a complicated
relation between those
four numbers and rotations and stretches.
But it's 4 equals 4 anyway.
And I guess
if you did 3 by 3s, oh,
3 by 3s, what would happen then?
So let
me take 3. Do you want to care for 3 by 3s?
It's sort of satisfying
to get 4 equal 4.
But now,
what do we get 3 by 3?
We got how many numbers here?
9.
GILBERT STRANGER. 9 numbers. Well, how many
here? That's usually the easy.
3. GILBERT STRANGER. 3.
So what's your guess for the
how many in a rotation?
In a 3D rotation, you
take a sphere and you rotate it.
How many
numbers to tell you what's what?
To tell you what you did?
3. We hope
3. Yeah, it's going to be 3, 3, and 3. For
the
three -dimensional world that we live in, so people who do rotations
for a living understand that a rotation in 3D, but how do you see this?
Roll, pitch, and yaw.
GILBERT STRANGER. Sorry? Roll, pitch, and yaw. GILBERT STRANGER.
Roll, pitch, and yaw. That sounds good. I mean, it's three words,
and we've got it, right?
OK. Yeah, roll, pitch,
and yaw. Yeah, I guess a pilot,
hopefully,
knows about those.
3.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah, which is roll,
when you're sort of like forward and back?
Roll, pitch, and yaw?
No, you guys don't know. Pitch is the up and down
one. GILBERT STRANGER. Pitch is the up and down one.
Roll is like, it's like a barrel hole. GILBERT STRANGER. Yes. And yaw is
your side side. GILBERT STRANGER. Oh, yaw, you stay in a plane, and you.
OK, beautiful.
Right, right.
And
that leads us to our four, four dimensions.
What's your guess on 4D?
Well, we could do the count again. If it was 4 by 4, we would have 16
numbers there. And in the middle, we always have an easy time with that.
That would
be 4. So we've got 12 left to share out.
So 6, somehow, 6 angles in four dimensions.
Well, we'll leave it there.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
OK,
so there's
the SVD, but without an example.
Examples,
you know, I would have to compute A transpose
A and find it. So the text will do that,
does it for a particular matrix.
Oh,
yeah, the text does it
for a matrix 3, 4, 0, 5 that
came out pretty well.
GILBERT STRANGER. A few facts we could learn, though.
So if I multiply all the eigenvalues together,
then
I, for a matrix A, what do I get?
I get the determinant.
What
if I multiply the singular values together?
Well, again, I get the determinant. You
can see it right away from the big formula.
Take determinants.
Well, assuming the matrix
A is square, so it's got a determinant.
Then I take determinants. The determinant of this
product, I can take the separate determinants.
That has determinant equal to 1,
an orthogonal matrix.
The determinant is 1.
And similarly here.
So the product of
the sigmas is also
the determinant. Yeah, yeah.
Sigma is also the determinant. The
product of the sigmas here will be 15. But
you'll find
that sigma 1 is smaller
than lambda 1.
So here are the eigenvalues.
Lambda 1 less
or equal to lambda 2,
say.
But
the singular
values are outside them.
Yeah. But they still multiply.
Sigma 1 times sigma 2
will still be 15.
And
that's the same as lambda 1 times lambda 2.
Yeah.
But overall, computing the examples of the SVD take more
time because, well, yeah, you just compute A transpose A.
And you've got the V's. And you're on your way. And
you have to take the square roots of the eigenvalues.
So that's the SVD as
a piece of pure math.
But of course, what we'll
do next time, starting right away,
is use SVD.
And let me tell you even
today the most important
pieces of the SVD. So what do I mean
by pieces of the SVD? I've got one
more blackboard still
to write on.
Here we go.
So let me write out A is the u's
times the sigmas,
sigmas 1 to r times the V's,
V transpose, V1 transpose
down to Vr transpose. So those are across.
Yeah, actually,
what
I've written here,
so you could say there
is a large, big economy.
There's a smaller size SVD
that has the real stuff that really counts.
And then there's
a larger SVD that has a whole lot of zeros.
So this would be
the smaller one,
m by r.
This would
be r by r. And these would all be positive.
And this would be r by n.
So that's only
using the r non -zeros.
All these
guys are greater than 0.
Then the other one,
we could fill out
to get a square
orthogonal matrix,
the sigmas,
and square
V's, V1 transpose to Vn transpose.
So what are the shapes now?
This shape is m by m.
It's a proper orthogonal matrix.
This one also, n by n. So this guy has to be,
this is the sigma now. So it has to be what size?
m
by n. That's the remaining space.
So it starts with the sigmas.
And then it's all zeros,
accounting for null space stuff.
Yeah, so you should really
see that these two are possible.
That all these zeros,
when you multiply out,
just give nothing. So that really, the
only thing that non -zero is in these bits.
But there is a complete one. So what
are these extra u's there in the null space
of A transpose or
A transpose A? Yeah, so two sizes,
the
large size and the small size. But then the
things that
count are all in there.
OK.
GILBERT STRANG So I was going to
do one more thing. And let me see what
it was.
So this is section 1 .8
of the notes.
And you'll see examples there.
And you'll see a second
approach to
the finding
the u's and V's and sigmas.
And I can tell you what that is. But maybe
just to
do something nice at the end,
let me
tell you about
another factorization of A
that's famous
in engineering.
And it's famous in
geometry.
So this is NEA is a u
sigma V transpose. We've got that.
Now, the other one that I'm thinking of, I'll tell you
its name. It's called the polar decomposition of a matrix.
And all I want you to
see is that it's virtually here.
So a polar means,
what's polar?
And for a complex number, what's the polar
form of a complex number?
e to
the i theta. It's e to the i theta times r.
Yeah. A real guy. So the real guy, r, will
translate into a symmetric guy.
And the e to the i theta will
translate into?
So what does e say?
What kind of a matrix
reminds you of e to the i theta?
Orthogonal.
Orthogonal. Size 1.
So orthogonal.
So that's a very nice.
Every matrix factors
into a symmetric matrix
times an orthogonal matrix.
And I have, of course,
described these
as the most important
classes of matrices. And here, we're saying
every matrix is
a s times a q.
And I'm also saying
that I can get that quickly out of the SVD.
So I just want to do it.
So I want to find an s and find a q out of
this.
So to get an s,
so let me
just start it. u sigma.
But now I'm looking for an s.
So what shall I take?
Put in now.
I better put in,
if I've got u sigma something and
I want it to be symmetric, I should put in?
u transpose would do it.
But then if
I put in u transpose, I've got to put in u.
So now I've got u sigma. u transpose u is the
identity. Now I've got to get v transpose.
And have I got what the polar decomposition
is asking for in this line?
So yeah, I think,
what have I got here?
Where's the s in this? So you see, I took
the SVD and I just put the identity in there.
Just shifted things a little.
And now where is the s that I can read off?
First rate.
GILBERT STRANGSKI. That's an s.
That's a symmetric matrix.
And where's the q? Well, I guess we can see
where the q has to be.
It's here.
Yeah.
Yeah, so just by sticking u transpose u and
looking and putting the parentheses right,
I recover that
decomposition of a matrix,
which in mechanical
engineering language tells me that any
strain can be,
which is
like stretching of an elastic thing,
has a symmetric kind of
a stretch and an internal twist.
So that's good.
Well, this was a
lot of 3, 6, 9 boards filled with matrices.
Well, it is
1806 -5, so maybe that's all right. But the
idea is to use them on
a matrix of data.
And I'll just
tell you the key fact.
The key fact. If I have
a big matrix of data,
A,
and if I want to
pull out of that matrix the important part.
So that's what data science
has to be doing. Out of a big matrix,
some part
of it is noise. Some part of it is signal.
I'm looking for the most important part of
the signal here.
So I'm looking
for the most important part of the matrix.
In a way, the biggest numbers.
But
of
course, I don't look at individual numbers.
So what's the biggest
part of the matrix?
What are the principal
components? Now we're really getting in.
If this is a,
you know, it could be data, and we want to
do statistics, or we want to see
what has high variance, what has low variance,
we'll do these connections with statistics.
But what's the important
part of the matrix? Well,
let me look at the u sigma
v transpose here. Yeah. Let me look at it.
So what's
the one most important part of that matrix?
The rank 1.
It's a rank 1 piece. So when I say a part,
of course, it's going to be a matrix part. So the
simple matrix building block is like a rank 1 matrix.
A something, something
transpose.
And what should I pull out of that as being the
most important rank 1 matrix that's in that product?
So I'll erase the
1 .8 while you think, what do I do
to pick out
the big deal,
the thing
that the data is telling me first?
Well, these are orthonormal.
No one is bigger than another one. These are
orthonormal. No one is bigger than another one. But
here I look here.
Which is the most important number?
Sigma 1. Sigma 1.
Sigma 1. So the part I pick out is this
biggest number times its row times its column.
So it's u 1
sigma 1 v 1 transpose
is the
top principal part of the matrix A. It's the leading part of the matrix
A. It's the rank 1, the biggest rank 1 part of the matrix is there.
So computing those three guys is the first
step to understanding the data.
Yeah.
So that's what's coming next is.
And I guess tomorrow
since they moved MIT
declared
Tuesday to be Monday.
They didn't change
Wednesday. So I'll see you tomorrow for the
principal components.
Good.